James Tener Curriculum Vitae

james.tener@anu.edu.au

http://math.tener.cc

CONTACT INFORMATION

Dr James E. Tener

Mathematical Sciences Institute

Hanna Neumann Building #145

Australian National University

Acton ACT 2601

Research interests

My work is motivated by conformal field theory (CFT), and my research program seeks to build a unified mathematical framework for the study of CFT, as well as to study new mathematical connections which arise as a result. Mathematical objects which arise include operator algebras, subfactors, functorial field theories, vertex operator algebras, quantum algebra and tensor categories, vector-valued modular forms, and complex function theory.

EMPLOYMENT

Australian National University

Senior Lecturer (January 2021 - present)

Lecturer (March 2019 - December 2020)

Mathematical Sciences Institute Research Fellow (July 2018 - March 2019)

University of California, Santa Barbara

Visiting Assistant Professor (September 2015 - April 2016, September 2016 - June 2018)

Max Planck Institute for Mathematics, Bonn

Postdoctoral Researcher (August 2014 - August 2015, June 2016 - August 2016)

VISITING POSITIONS

Research Member, MSRI Program on Quantum Symmetries (January 2020 - May 2020)

EDUCATION

University of California, Berkeley

PhD, Mathematics (September 2008 - May 2014)

Advisor: Vaughan F. R. Jones

Pomona College

BA, Mathematics (September 2004 - May 2008)

Magna cum laude, Phi Beta Kappa, math department award, and thesis award

EXTERNAL FUNDING

- 1. ARC Discovery Project DP200100067 "Physical realisation of enriched quantum symmetries," 2020 2023, co-Chief Investigator
- 2. AMSI Scientific Workshop Funding 2021, "The Mathematics of Conformal Field Theory II"
- 3. AMSI Scientific Workshop Funding 2019, "Subfactors in Sydney"
- 4. AMS-Simons Travel Grant 2017-2019
- 5. NSF Graduate Research Fellowship 2010-2012

Published articles and preprints

1. Unitary vertex algebras and Wightman conformal field theories

Commun. Math. Phys., to appear. arXiv:2203.10795.

(with C. Raymond and Y. Tanimoto)

2. Fusion and positivity in chiral conformal field theory submitted. arXiv:1910.08257.

- 3. Classification of extremal vertex operator algebras with two simple modules **J. Math. Phys.** 61 (2020), no. 5, 052302, 19 pp. arXiv:1811.02180 (with J. Connor Grady, Ching Hung Lam, and Hiroshi Yamauchi)
- 4. Representation theory in chiral conformal field theory: from fields to observables Selecta Math. (N.S.) (2019), 25:76. arXiv:1810.08168
- 5. Positivity and fusion of unitary modules for unitary vertex operator algebras RIMS Kôkyûroku (2018), no. 2086, 6-13.
- Singular values of weighted composition operators and second quantization
 Int. Math. Res. Not. IMRN (2018), no. 20, 6426-6441. arXiv:1612.03970
 (with Mihai Putinar)
- 7. On classification of extremal non-holomorphic conformal field theories

 J. Phys. A: Math. Theor., 50 (2017), 115204. arXiv:1611.04071 (with Zhenghan Wang)
- 8. Geometric realization of algebraic conformal field theories Adv. Math., 349 (2019), 488-563. arXiv:1611.01176
- 9. Construction of the unitary free fermion Segal CFT

 Commun. Math. Phys. 355 (2017), no. 2, 463-518. arXiv:1608.02095
- 10. Planar algebras in braided tensor categories

Mem. Amer. Math. Soc, to appear. arXiv:1607.06041 (with André Henriques and David Penneys)

- 11. Internal trace for module tensor categories over braided tensor categories

 Documenta Math., 21 (2016) 1089-1149. arXiv:1509.02937

 (with André Henriques and David Penneys)
- 12. Subfactors of index less than 5, part 4: vines

Int. J. Math., 23 (2012), no. 3, 1250017. arXiv:1010.3797 (with David Penneys)

- 13. Unitary equivalence to a complex symmetric matrix: low dimensions Lin. Alg. Appl., 437 (2012), no. 1, 271-284. arXiv:1104.4960 (with Stephan R. Garcia and Daniel Poore)
- 14. Unitary equivalence of a matrix to its transpose
 - J. Operator Theory, 68:1 (2012), 179-203. arXiv:0908.2107 (with Stephan R. Garcia)
- 15. Projections and idempotents with fixed diagonal and the homotopy problem for unit tight frames **Oper. Matrices**, 5 (2011) 139-155. arXiv:0906.0139 (with J. Giol, L.V. Kovalev, D. Larson and N. Nguyen)
- 16. Unitary equivalence to a complex symmetric matrix: an algorithm
 - J. Math. Anal. Appl., 341 (2008) 640-648. arXiv:0908.2201

SELECTED RECENT INTERNATIONAL RESEARCH CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS (SINCE JUNE 2016)

- 1. Australian and New Zealand Association of Mathematical Physics Annual Meeting Plenary talk (via Zoom), February 2022
- 2. MATRIX workshop on 2D Supersymmetric Theories and Related Topics MATRIX (via Zoom), January 2022
- 3. Workshop on Subfactors, Vertex Operator Algebras, and Tensor Categories Minicourse, IASM-BIRS, Hangzhou, China (via Zoom), September 2021
- 4. MSRI Introductory Workshop: Quantum Symmetries Mathematical Sciences Research Institute, Berkeley, USA, January 2020
- 5. Workshop on Subfactors and Applications Mathematisches Forschungsinstitut Oberwolfach, October 2019
- 6. Workshop on Operator Algebras and Quantum Physics Simons Center for Geometry and Physics, June 2019
- NCGOA/Shanks conference on Algebra and Geometry Quantized and Quantified Vanderbilt University, May 2019

- 8. Workshop on Subfactors and Fusion Categories
 - Banff International Research Station, October 2018
- 9. Workshop on Geometric and Categorical Aspects of CFTs
 - Casa Matemática Oaxaca, September 2018
- 10. Algebraic Methods in Mathematical Physics
 - CRM Montreal, July 2018
- 11. (Sub)Factors in Maui, May 2018
- 12. Workshop on algebraic combinatorics and representation theory of finite groups and vertex operator algebras
 - Kyoto RIMS, December 2017
- 13. Shanks workshop on subfactors and applications
 - Vanderbilt University, October 2017
- 14. Workshop on Subfactors, higher geometry, higher twists and almost Calabi-Yau algebras Isaac Newton Institute for Mathematical Sciences, Cambridge, March 2017
- 15. Southeastern Analysis Meeting 2017
 - UT Knoxville, March 2017
- 16. Berkeley-Tokyo Autumn School on Quantum Field Theory and Subfactors UC Berkeley, November 2016
- 17. Modular Categories–Their Representations, Classification, and Applications Casa Matemática Oaxaca, August 2016
- 18. Workshop on Von Neumann Algebras
 - Hausdorff Institute for Mathematics, Bonn, July 2016
- 19. Mathematics and Physics at the Crossroads trimester program seminar National Institute for Nuclear Physics, Frascati, June 2016

RECENT INVITED SEMINAR AND COLLOQUIUM TALKS (SINCE APRIL 2017)

- 1. Vanderbilt University Subfactor Seminar, December 2021
- 2. ANZ Geometry, Strings, and Fields Seminar, May 2021
- 3. Tokyo-Kyoto Operator Algebras Zoom Seminar, January 2021
- 4. Vanderbilt University Subfactor Seminar, November 2020
- 5. Wales Mathematical Physics-Physical Mathematics Zoom Seminar, July 2020
- 6. UC Davis Quantum Mathematics & Physics Seminar, February 2020
- 7. University of Rome Tor Vergata Operator Algebras Seminar, July 2019
- 8. University of Melbourne Pure Mathematics Seminar, March 2019
- 9. Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics, April 2018
- 10. University of Arizona Mathematics Colloquium, February 2018
- 11. UC Davis Seminar on Algebra & Discrete Mathematics, November 2017
- 12. OSU Seminar on Quantum Algebra & Quantum Topology, September 2017
- 13. OSU Seminar on Non-commutative Geometry & Operator Algebras, September 2017
- 14. Claremont Colleges Mathematics Colloquium, April 2017

SUPERVISION

- I am supervising ARC postdoctoral fellow Chris Raymond from 2020-2023.
- I am currently a supervisory panel member or chair for ANU PhD students Jaklyn Crilly, Amelia Han, Dominic Weiler, Ian Xiao (chair), and Tom Xu.
- ANU Honours supervision: Andy Yin (2021, University Medal).
- UCSB Honors supervision: J. Connor Grady (UCSB 2017-2018).

Conferences co-organised

- 1. The Mathematics of Conformal Field Theory II, July 2021. Funded by AMSI, AustMS, IAMP, and the MSI.
- 2. Subfactors in Sydney, February 2019. Funded by AMSI, AustMS, and the ARC.

- 3. Workshop on Quantum Symmetries, February 2019. Funded by the ARC.
- 4. Subfactors in Maui series, July 2019, 2017, 2013, and 2012. Funded by the NSF and DARPA.
- 5. Subfactor Theory in Mathematics and Physics, July 2014. Funded by DARPA.
- 6. QFTahoe Workshop, March 2013. Funded by the NSF.
- 7. Subfactors in Tahoe, February 2012. Funded by the NSF.

SERVICE AND ORGANIZATION

- Co-organiser for the MSI Special Year 2020 in Mathematical Physics
- Member of the MSI Equity and Diversity Committee and the MSI Higher Degree by Research (HDR) Committee
- Started the UC Santa Barbara seminar on quantum topology and quantum algebra, a research and learning seminar with significant interdisciplinary participation by graduate students from the mathematics, physics, and computer science departments.
- Served as a referee for 28 articles at 22 journals, including Annals of Mathematics, Journal of the AMS, Duke Mathematical Journal, Advances in Mathematics, International Mathematics Research Notices, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, and Communications in Mathematical Physics.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE AND AWARDS

- I am co-convener for the Spring session of MATH1014 Mathematics and Applications 2 (2020 present).
- I am the convener for MATH3228/6213 Advanced Complex Analysis (2018-present). In 2018 I was nominated by students for the Joint Colleges of Science Award for Teaching Excellence in 2018 (ineligible to win; the award requires at least three years of prior employment at ANU).
- I taught MATH3349/4349 Special Topics in Mathematics and Advanced Studies Courses on: "Operator algebras" (S2 2019) and "Lie groups and Lie algebras" (S2 2020).
- I co-taught MATH3351/6211 Advanced Topics in Mathematical Physics in S1 of 2019, on the subject of Vertex Operator Algebras.
- At UC Santa Barbara, I was the instructor of record for 11 courses, including Calculus II (5 times), Transition to Higher Mathematics (4 times), and upper division Linear Algebra (2 times). Course sizes range from 150-350 for calculus and 35-60 for proof-based courses. On a scale of 1=excellent to 5=poor, my average course rating by students was 1.2.
- As a graduate student at UC Berkeley, I was the instructor of record for Matrix Theory and Differential Equations, and a teaching assistant for Calculus II, Precalculus, Matrix Theory, and Linear Algebra. I received an Outstanding Graduate Student Instructor award.